James Dean died today.
He had lived with a great hunger.
What do you say?
His
last film was Giants.
When it opened more than a year after
his death, Hollywood celebrated with the
biggest premiere in a decade.
James Dean was buil below two other
stars, but the night belonged to him.
As the picture opened at the first runs
in the neighborhoods,
everyone came to take a final look
and gave him an ovation each time his
face appeared.
They had made James Dean
and they wouldn't let him go.
To keep him close, they made a legend in
his name.
From
Maine to Manila, from Tokyo to Rome,
he seemed to express some of the things
they couldn't find the words for.
Rage,
rebellion,
hope,
the lonely awareness that growing up is
pain.
They wore what he wore.
They walked as he walked.
They played the parts they saw him play.
And they searched for the answers. they
thought he was searching for.
Some found a kinship they had never
known before.
Youth mourned itself in the passing of
James Dean.
Because he died young and belonged to no
one, every girl could feel that he
belonged to her alone. Because he died
violently,
every boy could use him as a warning to
his parents. If you don't start
understanding me,
I could go the same way.
A hero
made of their loneliness.
A legend woven from their restlessness,
their energy, their despair. What is the
hero to do with James Dean?
What is the legend to do with his life?
To those who made the hero,
to those who wo the legend, this picture
is dedicated
with affection
and with hope.
If there is an answer,
it belongs to them.
To separate hero from legend, we must go
back to Fairmount, Indiana,
the land where he spent his youth.
A Hollywood newsman once asked whether
Fairmount is a quaint little town.
Fair Mount is little, but it isn't
quaint.
It's a useful town used long and well by
useful people.
farmers mostly.
One of them told us
>> it's a pretty good town. Good place for
boy to grow up.
>> There are two ways of coming to
Fairmont.
We came by road.
Jimmy Dean came by rail.
He was 9 years old.
The body of his mother was on the same
train.
It was a lonesome way to come home.
For the years of his life, Jimmy looked
to this town and the farms around it as
his source and his beginning.
a quiet land to come home to, a place to
replenish himself.
The road he traveled that first day
became an artery of his life.
It lies between cornfields and meadows,
passes close to the Quaker church where
he prayed,
passes Mr. Carter's motorcycle shop
where he learned about speed
and the cemetery with its generations of
Windslows and Deans.
The road comes at last to the heart of
his childhood,
the Winslow farm,
home of his aunt or tense, his uncle
Marcus, and his cousin Marky.
The farm seemed strange to him at first
and the house seemed very big.
He was left by himself to get over his
grief.
He woke up crying from a nightmare.
He was dreaming of his mother. He would
always dream of her.
>> Mr. Winslow.
>> Yes.
>> How big a farm have you got? 350 acres.
>> What crops do you grow?
>> Mostly corn and some oats and some hay.
>> And Jimmy was raised here?
>> Yes. Came here when he was nine and left
when he was 18.
>> Was he much help on the farm?
>> Very good help with machinery and was
very good with livestock up to his
junior year of high school.
>> When did you first notice his acting
talent?
>> Well, I'd say his last year of school
when he spoke in the National Forensic
League. He won the National Peru,
Indiana. And then he went on to
Longmont, Colorado and spoke in the
national there.
>> Have you any idea where his talent came
from, Marcus?
>> Well, I couldn't say about that. That's
just like due south. One having seven
pigs and one having 15. Why Why does it
happen?
>> Um, what about this house? Is it old?
>> It was built in 194 and there's about 15
rooms in it. Would you care to go over
and meet my wife?
I want you to meet my wife, Mrs.
Winslow.
>> Mrs. Winslow, would you tell us why
Jimmy came to live with you?
>> Well, his mother died and we had always
thought a lot of Jimmy. And when we
learned that uh his mother would not
recover, we asked for him. we have uh
read where he was sort of pushed off
onto us but uh that is not true. We um
we wanted him. We were happy to have him
and uh he seemed to be perfectly
satisfied.
>> The older generations on the other side
of town, Grandma and Grandpa Dean,
>> look at here. What came today? Oh, isn't
that beautiful?
>> Where did that come from?
>> From Japan.
>> Let's hear what came yesterday.
I get so much mail from Japan.
>> Have you any of Jimmy's baby pictures,
Mrs. Dean?
>> Here's Jimmy when he was 2 months old.
And then here he is again when he was 2
and a half years old.
And here's a picture of him on a pony
when uh he was 6 years old out in Cal
he's out in California at that time.
And here he is when he was playing in
high school on that high school
basketball team. and
he uh that does his uh third year in
high school.
>> This is Fair Mount High School.
>> His coach said,
>> "Jimmy wasn't too coachable.
You had to be careful about changing his
style, and I learned not to embarrass
him in front of the other boys."
>> He racked up 40 points in three games.
He had been an enormous baby, but for
some reason he grew up to be a very
little boy. And because he was little,
he tried all the harder and made the
baseball team and smashed the pole vault
record for Grant County
and quit. Uncle Marcus said,
>> "Uh, Jimmy broke 15 pair of eyeglasses
just trying to be an athlete. You break
them as fast as I could get them. Once
in a while, he had to bring these home.
I was called to see the principal so
many times I almost moved into her
office.
For the first time, Jimmy began to show
another side.
He painted the things he saw and tried
to put feeling into them.
And he succeeded once when he painted
his loneliness,
but it wasn't enough for him.
He felt more at home on the stage where
he could pretend to be somebody else.
Adeline Null was his acting teacher. She
coached him in forensics. Miss Null,
what did Jimmy recite at the state
forensic meet?
>> Jimmy chose the madman story by Charles
Dickens for his reading.
>> What special thing set him apart?
Well, uh, Jimmy, as in anything he did,
put in his whole heart. He, um,
uh, had wonderful use of his eyes. I
think his eyes were one of the most
effective things, uh, that made an
impression on the teachers at the meet.
one.
>> I have a picture here of an orchid that
Jimmy painted for me. It was the day
following the first showing of the
junior play. The cast gave me this
orchid or gave me an orchid and uh it
was the first orchid I'd ever received.
Jimmy who made the presentation then
came over and gave me a kiss. The next
day he came into my classroom and asked
for the orchid. I didn't know what the
child wanted. He took it to the art
class and painted this for me which I
have prized through the years. Then he
said, "Now you can keep your orchid
forever. It's one of my prized
possessions."
>> Mr. Carter, who owns this shop, says
Jimmy was really a pistol. They called
him one speed Dean. One speed wide open.
Mr. Carter, would you show us Jimmy's
motorcycle?
>> Yes, sir. This motorcycle here is the
first one he ever owned. This is a 1947
check jobs made in Czech old Shiovakia.
It's rated at a horse and a half
horsepower, and it will run
approximately 50 m an hour.
>> How old was he when he got it?
>> Uh 15.
>> Where did he race his bike?
Uh we had a
uh field enjoying the shop here that uh
we got off the neighbor. We rented it
and we built a small track on it and
Jimmy used to go over there and run
around this track which was absolutely
no official track but just something to
play on. He used to broadside it around
and we had a great time with him.
He at one time came in here. I had an a
public address system and he came in
here and wanted to know if he could talk
on it and I told him yes, he could. So
he got back in the corner of the shop
here and put a speaker outside and he
put on a race, an imaginary race. And he
would line the fellas up on the track
and tell what kind of motor they were
riding and and tell about the takeoff on
them and about somebody road sliding a
little too much in the corner and look
out they're going to fall and he'd
holler and then laugh and say down he
goes. He was really describing the race.
He really had a a great imagination.
Bing Traster owns his own nursery on the
south side of town. He and Jimmy had one
thing in common, a sense of humor.
>> Mr. Traster, have you known the Dean
family very long?
>> Yes, I was personally acquainted with
four generations of the Dean family.
>> Did you know Jimmy Dean?
>> Yeah, I knew Jimmy Dean. any of one of
the boys around town and knew them all,
of course, naturally.
>> How did Jimmy impress you, Bing?
>> Well, yes, Jimmy had a little something
up here that the old boys don't have or
haven't had. I haven't noticed it in
them. His uh the old Dean Homestead is
out here mile and a half south where his
father was born and his grandfather also
lived there. And his boy, I don't know
whether grandfather's born there or not,
but great-grandfather lived there.
And uh Jimmy kind of get down the blues.
He get on his motorcycle while here at
the old home place, the old homestead
and meditate a while. It seemed to
derive a certain amount of comfort from
it being where the ancestor used to
live. And he had spiritual values that
the average kid didn't seem to have.
>> Is there anything out there now?
>> Shade trees, a few fruit trees, weeds,
and the farms changed hands. The Cadine
people lived there.
>> What about Calaldine?
>> Well, Calaldine was an auctioneer. He
was a farmer to begin with and he went
someplace up here about Vanco which is
the northern part of Wbash County to
attend a sale
and the regular auctioneer didn't show
up so they called for volunteers and Cal
volunteered and got up and cried the
sale and made a big success and he was a
sail car from their own.
>> He was Jimmy's grandfather.
>> No, he was Jimmy Dean's
greatgrandfather. His great-grandfather
man about my size a little larger. He a
little more bay window.
>> You think he got his talent from Cal
Dean?
>> Well, yes. Jimmy got quite a bit of
talent from the Dean family there, old
showman. Uh, old Calaldian, the
great-grandfather of Jimmy. He was quite
a showman himself. And uh,
old Calaldian had a cousin lived out at
Summerville had south 5 miles. He was
also a sail crier and he was good
getting off stories. Some a little off
color and get by with them all like the
crowd laughing and Cal could do the same
thing.
He seemed to derive a certain amount of
comfort from it, being where the
ancestors used to live.
Season after season, Marcus watched him
grow and gathered in his harvest.
But of all the harvests his farm had
grown, the most plentiful were his
children, and he looked upon Jimmy as
one of them.
He seemed like a happy boy. Not quite
like the others perhaps, but not so
remarkable either.
A boy who liked his garden and was proud
of the things he grew.
A boy who liked to fool around with his
little cousin Marky, who grew up to be
his brother. A boy who liked animals
because they accepted him as he was.
and they were gentle and who had a dog
he named Tuck for reasons of his own.
But no boy is exactly what he seems.
And Jimmy had his own secret world. He
left only three doorways for us to look
into it.
A tree in an empty landscape which he
turned to in his loneliness.
A mother's grave which he turned to in
his questioning and in his dreams
and a clipping he saved to trace the
steps of his fulfillment.
These are the needs. It says
the need for love and security.
The need for creative expression.
the need for recognition
and self-esteem. He made this statue and
he called it self,
but it had no face.
It seemed like something happened to
Jimmy. He started pulling into himself
and didn't share things with us anymore.
But maybe that's just growing up.
Nothing he tried satisfied his hunger.
He began to say goodbye to Fairmount in
his childhood.
Restlessness possessed him.
He must move. Move somewhere.
And motion makes any road seem right.
He must find a face for the image he
called self.
Every block in Los Angeles had more
people in it than the whole town of
Fairmont and all the farms around it put
together.
And none of them had ever heard of Jimmy
Dean.
He could be anything here.
He looked down at the city and planned a
strategy as he had often looked at a
winter field and considered the crops he
would grow.
Maybe if he behaved like everybody else,
he might belong somewhere
and become something
and he came down the hill.
He registered at UCLA and he began as a
model student. He was proud of himself,
so he wrote a letter home. Here's a
letter I got from uh Jimmy when he was
going to school in UCLA out in
California.
>> He wrote that he was very busy and
working awfully hard and the semester
just ahead was even harder.
His grades were fine for a change. Four
B's, one C, and an A.
He was taking lots of drama in school,
and he had just landed a good part in a
student play.
And he said to his grandmother that he
was really finding out one thing that an
actor must be an intellectual which
takes years to develop.
If he was going to conform, he'd do it
all the way. So he tried to do it
royally and joined Sigmanu. What's your
position, Bob?
>> I'm a president of Sigu fraternity. Uh I
pledged the house in February 1952 and
Dean pledged in 50 I think September
1950.
Uh uh we uh looked through the files
uh a couple months ago to see whether we
had anything uh from Dean and this is
his pledge application. This is an
application to the national in the
financial records. We uh uh after his
four months of pledging, we noticed that
he has a $45 deficit on his house bill,
which he never paid, of course.
>> John, when did you meet Jimmy?
>> Uh I first met uh Jimmy Dean in fall of
1950 during rushing and I was quite
impressed with him. I talked to him
several times during rushing and he
seemed real sincere though he was quiet.
Well, he pledged and then uh it became
quite apparent after a couple weeks that
uh the controls that are exerted over a
pledge were a little bit he just
couldn't accept them was the main
problem. Things like home missing Monday
night meetings.
Uh he had his original or his final bit
of trouble I guess you would say and it
ended up in a fist fight between he and
one of the pledges and he walked out in
a huff and that was the last anyone ever
saw of him.
Who am I? He wondered.
I don't want to be alone.
I don't want to be different.
I need people. But I keep pushing them
away.
I've got all this love to give.
He took his envy to the beach.
He looked at the ocean
and he was jealous of its power.
He envied the Gulves for having found
each other.
He envied them their freedom and their
solitary flights.
Suddenly he knew
that as an actor he could be the ocean
and flood everything with his power.
As an actor, he could be a gull and rise
higher than any living thing.
He would become an actor, really an
actor. He would conquer New York and
press the theater to his feet. Then he
would come back and conquer Hollywood.
He would rise so high he would almost
vanish. And everyone would beg him to
come back.
and he saw a dead bird in the sand and
wept for it.
But he was on his way.
Jimmy Dean was going to be somebody.
He needed Carfair to get to New York. So
he did his first movie. It was filmed on
the merrygoround in Griffith Park. And
Jimmy was an extra. A one-minute
commercial for a soft drink company.
The ride took him all the way to Time
Square.
The city showed him its 9 million faces,
and he tried to absorb them all.
He found them on subways
and in the bars,
on the waterfronts.
Greenwich Village
in places where it wasn't safe to go.
He tried to feel what he thought they
felt.
I love
I belong to someone.
I don't belong to anyone.
Always the onlooker.
always just outside.
He began to push at the walls of his own
isolation and break into the lives
around him.
He would borrow a laugh,
a sudden gesture,
the droop of sadness.
People were his food, and he ate them up
hungrily
to help him build his actor's face.
His appetites were large, but he was
never quite full.
Neither was his suitcase.
He thought sleep was a waste of time,
and if he slept, he might miss
something.
afraid of his solitude,
afraid of his dreams.
He prowled through the nights like a
hunter.
He'd borrow a paper to see what was
playing on 42nd Street.
And he'd go to three features to stretch
out the night.
Sometimes he'd register at a small hotel
that was left behind when Glamour moved
up town.
And when his money ran out, so did he.
But he found a second home,
Jerry's Bar, where he was always
welcome.
The gentleman on the left is Louie. He
was Jimmy's favorite waiter. The one on
the right is Jerry. He owns the place.
How was his appetite, Jerry?
>> Always spaghetti. He was a spaghetti
boy. He said, "I'm going to be an
Italian by spaghetti eater." He laughed
like hell because he thought he thought
he could roll him just like an Italian.
I taught him once and he he follow
again. Follow again. He just laughed
every time I looked at him. He parrolled
spaghetti just like he was born in
Naples, Italy.
>> Care to comment, Louis?
>> Well, I can say plenty about him because
he used to come in at times, you know,
that uh he didn't have anything. That's
when he first started. And he used to
ask me or ask the boss, is it all right
if I get a plate of spaghetti and you
made good for it? So the boss said,
"Sure, go ahead. Give it to him." You
know, and so things and so on.
>> Did he ask for anything else?
>> Yes, he did. Many times I give him that
money and he always paid me back. When
he made it, he paid me back.
>> Then he promised me. He says, "Louis
says if I ever get up on top," he says,
"I'm going to take care of you."
>> Could you tell us about the champagne
episode?
>> You mean when he come in with the bottle
of champagne that he bought from the
outside? Well, he came in at night. He
had the champagne wrapped up in a bag, a
package. And he told me, he says, "Lou,
come in with three other boys." And he
says, "Louis," he says, "Uh, give me a
few glasses here and open a spotlight
for me." I said, "Jimmy," I said, "Look,
it's against the rules of the house and
I can't do that for you." But if I do
that for you, I said I lose my job cuz
we carry champagne in here and you can't
bring it in from outside, you know, just
buy it here. You take that home with you
and uh then you buy some here and then
you drink it up. So you got so peasy
that you open the bottle, you ran to the
beer cooler and you dumped the whole
bottle in the beer cooler. Then after
that he said, "Well, bring me some
champagne." I said, "What do you want? A
quart, a fifth, or you want splits?" He
says, "Bring us two splits." Then he
bought two splits and he says, "Well,
divide it up between us." There was four
of them.
>> Did he ever bring his drums?
>> Oh, bungalow drum. He used to come in,
you know, for a couple of nights. He
used to bring it on his back. He used to
carry on his back, you know, with a
strap, dungarees, you know, and the
thing he looked like uh nothing, you
know, a lot of people used to ask me in
a place they say, "Who's that boy
there?"
He go, "Boy, he's going to be a big
someday." Now they say, "You're crazy."
Said it's Jimmy Dean. you know that
nobody wanted to believe it, you know.
So anyway, he come in with the drums and
he started rap on the drums, you know,
and he was making so much noise that
everybody was getting annoyed in the
place, you know. So I went over to him.
I said, "Jimmy, I'm sorry, but we can't
do that." And he got peeved again. You
know, he was a boy that uh I don't know,
he was hard to understand, you know.
>> It's a wonderful, generous city behind
the brick and mortar, Jimmy said. And
it's full of perceptive,
wonderful people.
People he wanted to work with.
People he wanted to know.
People he hoped would respect him one
day,
whose names were written in lights. And
he wondered how it would feel.
Leonard Rosenman was a young composer
who later created the music for East of
Eden and Rebel Without a Cause.
To save expenses, they took an apartment
together.
It was a fivestory walk up with port
holes like a ship.
Jimmy called it a waste basket with
walls.
If he pressed his head against the
window in a certain way and squinted
through one eye, he had a grand view of
Central Park.
It wasn't Indiana, but it was full of
trees he could sit under.
He began to imagine himself as a deep
thinker. "An actor must know everything
about everything," he said. But in his
hurry, he settled for less.
He stood still long enough to make
friends with a girl.
>> Arlene sex.
>> I knew him
once. I told him I loved him, but he
pretended he didn't hear.
And then he said, "You can't love me."
And I don't think anyone can yet.
We listen to music together. Bart talk
and Shernburgg and Mozart.
And he read me the little prince. It was
his favorite book
because it was about him. Told about a
little boy who came from a star where he
planted a rose.
Boy loved to look at the stars because
he had faith that somewhere on one of
them a single rose was hoping he'd come
home.
Then the little boy died.
Well, once he was playing his recorder,
he hit a wrong note and he burst out
crying. That made me cry, too.
And all of a sudden, he'd do something
no one ever thought of doing before. So,
you'd have to laugh at that. Then, I'd
see his mind go away and hide somewhere.
And I'd ask him what he was thinking.
He'd say, "I'm thinking of my mother."
And I'd say, "Do you miss her?"
and you'd say, "Come on, let's get a hot
dog." We would.
>> I always had the feeling I should open
the window and say, "Fly bird."
He pounded the pavements looking for
work.
And he wrote letters home.
And when he wrote to Ador Tents, he
always started with dear mom. and he
said he felt ashamed to be always
needing something, but if she was going
to send him a Christmas present anyway,
he'd rather have the money.
And he wrote to them all and said he
could never forget what they'd done for
him and that he wanted to repay them by
being a big success. And he tried not to
take too long.
And he finally made it.
>> Yes. One night, one night it was a
Sunday night. I walk in the place and
Jimmy Dean is a very stormy night
outside. Rain and Jimmy Dean has got a
pair of dang and a pair of sneakers all
soaking and wet. He got no fish shirt
and was a lumberjack non shaved uncom.
He's bringing double scotch and Louisie
was serving him. I said, "What are you
doing? Go to hell yourself?" Which was a
nice boy. You always took my advice. He
says, "No, papa." He says, "I I I got to
do something tonight. I want to look
very natural." He said, and he was
smiling at me. I said, "What are you
going to do? I told you was doing
something crazy." He says, "No, I got to
do something a little while. I surprise
you." So time came and he he got up. He
said, "Look, I'm going to be right back
to set the television at such such
station." We set the television. He
appear on Gman in action as a drunken
waterfront man. Just the way I got up
out of my seat, came back about 20
minutes late. He laughs like hell. Says,
"Now you go and buy me a double shot.
You I want with me. Is that all right?"
>> Jimmy developed a reputation as the most
troublesome young actor in New York.
When he came to rehearsal, his directors
never knew from minute to minute just
what he planned to do next,
or if he planned to come at all.
An actor said,
>> "He plays my nephew, and I'm supposed to
say you will forgive him if he acts a
little strange." "But how can I say he
acts a little strange when the son of a
gun is crazy?"
"Why do I do these things?" Jimmy
wondered.
And he really didn't know.
But he wanted more than television
and the small building on an
unimpressive street drew him again and
again.
The actor's studio.
Lee Strawber taught here. So did Kazan.
To be the best, he had to learn from the
best. He would prepare himself. He tried
a new experiment.
He got a haircut
and joined a dance class to get his feet
out of the furrows and to find an
actor's grace.
During this time of preparation, he met
a taxi cab driver, Arie Langanger, who
became his friend. First time I met
Jimmy, uh,
he had a date with a girlfriend of mine.
Brought her over to meet me. I didn't
know he was who he was. He hadn't been
in the movies yet. He was on TV, but I
drove a hack at night and I never I
never saw him. So, just a guy.
He came in the house. He was very shy
and uh didn't impress me.
And uh, we went down. We bought some
food which I paid for
and uh we uh got up the house, we ate.
He wasn't included in part of there was
four of us and he was like out of it. He
was always studying people taking their
physical characteristics and using it in
his acting. like uh the day after one
night after I met him, he told somebody
the next day when he went up for I think
it was battlecry audition and he was
going to use something he was he was
going to make believe he use army cuz uh
that day he decided he would take
certain things from me uh like I used to
go like this
he would use that and he he used objects
beautifully he was always he had a way
of diverting attention from other people
like uh somebody else was reading a
line, he he'd do something like uh you
know like this and always you know be
looking at that and he was that was part
of his sensitivity.
He felt he was ready to audition for the
actor's studio.
So he went to see an actress named Chris
White. She was trying for the studio too
and he hoped she might help him. She
said,
>> "I wrote the scene for our audition,
which Jimmy promptly rewrote. We
rehearsed for two months, and he never
played the scene the same way twice,
even the day of the audition, but it was
a terrific improvisation, and they let
us stay on 3 minutes longer than anyone
else."
The letter he wrote home was full of
excitement and repetitions. He was proud
to announce his membership in the actor
studio, he wrote. It was a great honor
to be in a great school full of great
people like Marlon Brando and Monty Clif
and June Havoc.
And he James Dean was the youngest to
belong. It was great.
Lee Strawber said he was a natural actor
but very shy, sensitive about people
getting too close to him.
And when Strawberry criticized the scene
he did, Jimmy walked out of the actor's
studio and never performed there again.
He was offered a contract for his first
Broadway play.
Mr. Ross was in charge of press
relations for See the Jaguar. Well, um
I'm afraid that Jimmy Dean's first bath
of fire in the theater wasn't too uh
glorious. The play opened on a Thursday
night, seem to remember, and closed on a
Saturday night that same week. The
critics didn't like it. The critics
didn't understand it.
Next performance was in Jed's the
immoralist by Ruth and Augustus Gets.
Jimmy was part of an excellent cast.
Geraldine Paige, Louis Jordan, and David
J. Stewart. He played an Arab boy and
had to perform a seductive, insinuating
dance.
The Arab boy lived in a date grove on
the desert and came between a husband
and his wife and destroyed them both. On
opening night, the critics greeted him
as a brilliant and promising young star.
And he remembered the ocean he had
envied,
and the seagull in its flight,
and he knew he had found his power.
The theater and its people made him
welcome,
but he fought with the producer and quit
the show two weeks after it opened.
In New York, he had won the reputation
of a rebel.
He had denied himself all the things he
wanted most.
He had denied himself the pleasure of
his own success,
the respect
of people who had been his gods.
He had denied himself.
"Why do I destroy the things I build?"
he asked.
and he sat under a tree in Central Park
and wrote a letter to his cousin Marky
to thank him for some drawings he had
sent. But he was really writing to
himself.
Dear Marky,
we asked Marky if he remembered what
Jimmy wrote to him. And this is what
Marky told us. Jim said he wanted to
thank me for my drawings,
but he had to warn me about something.
He said it's easy to draw pictures of
soldiers and people shooting guns
and jails where they lock people up. But
he said I shouldn't draw these things
because they aren't good to draw. He
told me that I live on a land that God
has blessed with trees and rivers and
the ocean and all the animals I see and
houses where people can open the door
whenever they want to.
He said, "These are the things to draw,
and all I have to do is look around to
see."
And Marky told us how Jimmy had ended
his letter.
These things are harder to draw because
they are harder to grow.
>> My love to you Marky Jim.
>> Then he went up to the bra to see Jimmy
went to California to make pictures.
>> When was the last time you saw him,
Louie?
Hi. The last time I saw Jimmy is uh
when he went to California, he went to
Hollywood to make uh the big picture.
You know, that was the last time. And
then we had a nice party there for him.
A lot of people used to ask me in a
place, they say, "Who's that boy there?"
This Jimmy Dean, you know, he was a boy
that uh I don't know, he was hard to
understand. You know,
>> he was flying to his director, Ilia
Kazan.
When he chose Jimmy for the part in East
of Eden, Kazan said Jimmy was it. He was
vengeful. He had a sense of aloneeness.
He was suspicious.
He let you into a private club that had
only a few members.
Fly bird. Fly.
Fly bird.
He had come to the most dangerous
battleground of his life. Suspicious of
everyone, he took note of possible
enemies. The probing eye,
the listening ear,
the audience.
Watch out.
They can corrupt you.
They can pick you apart and put you back
together.
They can make you change.
He moved into his studio dressing room.
He kept a revolver which made him feel
safe.
But they found it and took it away.
He bought a new motorcycle so he could
move fast and alone.
He dressed as he always had because old
clothes were familiar things in an
unfamiliar place.
And he never judged a man by what he
wore.
But Hollywood did.
When he roamed its streets as he had
roamed Time Square, Hollywood said,
"Look at those boots. Who does he think
he is? Marlon Brando.
But the more they criticize, the more he
refused to change.
He felt that he owned so little he had
to defend it a lot.
Possessions were important to him.
To be able to buy the things he wanted
meant that someone was treating him
nicely, even if that someone was only
himself.
And when a stranger broke his headlight,
he cried like a child, as if he were the
one who was injured.
The villa Capri reminded him of Jerry's
bar in New York.
He felt safe there
because Paty and Billy were almost like
Jerry and Lou. They took him as he was
and accepted his suspicion without
comment.
Well, he used to come in almost every
night
and uh
he used to come in really after work and
he used to he used to dress with
overalls do used to do see any man
working dick ditches you know nothing
fancy in fact I never saw him dressed up
good really
>> did he have a sense of humor
>> he oh very much in fact sometime he come
in at night and sit down on this food
and talk a few words in Italian. He like
to talk Italian too, you know, a little
bit. He tried to learn Italian a little
bit. And uh sometime we don't have no we
were so busy. He used to go eat in the
kitchen
and uh never bother him nothing. This
was really fine man, a fine boy. Nothing
about him. We get most of all the stars
in Hollywood and Jimmy being here almost
every night used to meet them all here
and he was quite a favorite of these
stars.
>> Milton Burl,
Sammy Davis Jr. and he tried to believe
it when they said they liked him.
When he started work on East of Eden, he
discovered that a movie actor has to get
up earlier than anyone else.
He trusted Kazan because Kazan seemed to
trust him and allowed him to pace his
own performance.
They had signals.
When Jimmy was ready, he'd whistle.
And Kazan knew he could begin.
>> Standby.
>> Action.
William Zinda's review in the New York
Herald Trabune was not only a
description of his role in East of Eden,
but also of Jimmy himself. He wrote,
"Everything about him suggests the
lonely, misunderstood 19-year-old.
He has the wounded look of an orphan
trying to piece together the shabby
facts of his heritage.
Occasionally, he smiles as if it's some
dark joke known only to himself.
You sense badness in him, but you also
like him.
Before Eden was finished, Hollywood knew
that James Dean was the most important
new star of the year.
It gave him the courage to take a chance
on himself
and to fall in love for the first time.
She entered his longing and his life,
bringing a depth of compassion and a
hopeful, half-remembered tenderness.
She quieted his violence, and he felt
himself grow still.
And for the first time, he found the
timid belief that life was possible.
He slept through the nights without
dreaming.
He began to enjoy.
He began to share.
It made him very happy.
>> And he found a friend. He said, "I have
one very close friend and I feel so
happy." Isn't that strange?
>> Lou Bracker lived in a secure home with
a real mother and father and three hot
meals a day.
>> Come on.
Hi, Lou. What's your dog's name?
>> Uh, that's Micolina. She's a uh
three-year-old Labrador
and uh she was about a year old when
Jimmy was here.
Used to spend a whole summer trying to
get her to dive off the board, but she
never would do it. Still doesn't, as a
matter of fact.
>> Lou invited us inside to show us some of
Jimmy's things. Here's a box of uh stuff
that Jimmy gave for to me to keep before
he uh about two weeks before his
accident. It's u just personal
belongings. Uh here's a bunch of fan
mail that came to him personally and he
didn't turn it over to his fan mail
service. Here's a couple of uh snapshots
of Jimmy working on his car before the
uh Palm Springs road races in 1955,
which was his first road race.
Here's a guy that wanted to sell him an
oil well,
some phone numbers, and a Diner Club
bill.
Here's a little write up uh after the
Palm Springs races.
It says, "Third spot went to young
motion picture actor James Dean driving
his first race in a Porsche Speedster."
Um, here's a note from his laundry
saying that a sheet was damaged and they
couldn't launder it.
Bank statement with a telephone number
on the end of it.
More telephone numbers.
There's something from a screen actor's
gill letting him know that his dues are
jumping.
Telephone number. I don't know how Jimmy
ever kept track of his telephone numbers
because you never could be quite sure
where yours was written cuz it was the
way he used to file things. Just throw
them in a box. And uh
might surprise you or the audience
to know that Jimmy was fantastically
interested in business. He uh himself
always wanted to uh have his own
company.
Matter of fact, he wanted to become a
director. He felt that um there was more
room for self-expression certainly more
freedom of movement in in being in
direction than in acting.
So actually he was learning he was
learning a little more how to get along
with uh strangers and um
also uh the things that uh that he would
read about himself hurt him. uh he he
would be bothered when someone would say
that he was uh uh mean and um uh
disrespectful because actually he
wasn't. It was just they took silence to
mean that he cared little or nothing for
him. They didn't have the insight or
didn't care to to exercise their insight
in knowing that here was a shy boy that
just didn't know how to approach him.
And they didn't make instead of making
an attempt to approach him, they just
said, "Well, they just wrote him off."
It seemed that he was always losing the
people he cared for most deeply.
So it had always been. So it would
always be.
So be it.
He became the night wanderer once again,
looking for a place to unload his
tenderness and finding none. So he
bought a horse and gave it a manger of
oats and the measure of love. Lou
Bracker has it now. It runs free in
Santa Barbara Meadows. He found some
relief in racing the Porsche car he
bought as a consolation prize to
himself.
in his drums
and in occasional people. Glenn Kramer,
an actor.
>> Glenn, what happened if no one paid
attention to Jimmy on dates, for
instance?
Well, uh,
I I don't know too much about his
dating. I I know one or two of the girls
he he had dated.
>> Lily Cardell, an actress. Where are you
from, Lily?
>> I'm from Sweden. I was born in
Stockholm.
>> What was he like with you?
Well, now and then we could go into a
restaurant like uh Villa Capri, for
instance, which was our favorite place
to dine, and uh could all of a sudden
just leave the table and go away without
any excuse or anything and move over to
some old buddy of his and start talking
about cars or something like that and be
gone for a half hour. And he was very al
also very moody. It could one minute be
deep in thought about something and just
snap out of it and and the next minute
it could be up on the floor dancing,
laughing, making some joke of some kind,
you know, and it was just no no use of
getting mad at him for that kind of
thing because that just didn't do any
good. You just had to understand that
that was the way he was.
>> That was the way he was. Nick Ray, the
director of Rebel Without a Cause, knew
what Kazan meant when he said Jimmy
belonged to a private club that had only
a few members.
And he had his own way of winning the
boy's trust. He took him to meet the
rebels.
Though Jimmy could find the reality of
young Jim Stark, the character he was
about to play.
Rebel Without a Cause was a drama of
rage.
of a young man suffering
and his battle to bring comfort to an
outcast boy who needed him and to a girl
who had never known love.
He could expose through Jim Stark the
things he had to conceal as Jimmy Dean.
But when the film was finished,
Jim Stark was gone.
The performance was over.
Success was nothing more than the
concealing leaf which covered the tree
of his loneliness.
And after every job
the tree was bare,
and winter returned to chill him.
He knew that he could never hide from
pain.
But if he kept busy, he might forget it.
So he threw himself hopefully at each
new day and tried to connect with life.
He tried to record life with his camera.
He became interested in bull fighting
because he fancied himself for Matador,
a solitary figure who brought danger to
its knees.
To test the limits of life, he had to
approach the borders of death.
He beat out the rhythms of his life on a
drum
and he laughed.
His days thundered with the roar of his
experiments.
Heat.
HEAT.
But these were only echoes of the thing
he never found.
The thing which kept escaping him,
the thing that had no face,
himself.
The star was rushing home. Before he
could go any further, he knew he must
face himself. And he could only do it in
Fairmount.
He must know why he found no happiness
in his own success.
Why he seemed always to lose the ones he
loved.
A writer friend had spelled out the
question for him just the week before.
>> They were having dinner together.
No, I can't explain you, but I think I
can draw a picture of yourself if you
don't get sore.
See, that's a thing we all have that we
don't want anyone to see. It's very
tender. Our our secret self, if you want
to call it that. And
that's the thing we have to protect.
Now, most of us put a wall around it.
Mirrors like this. See, if we don't
trust people, we use it to keep them out
so they can't hurt us. But you, look
what you've got. Mirrors aren't enough
for you. You've got to have this, too. A
second wall. And it's all covered with
thorns and spangles and shockers to
dazzle people so they say, "Boy, he's
really a hot apple. Look how interesting
he is." Here you meet a director you
really respect, and you do some darn
fool thing that scares him off. Here you
meet a businessman and you say, "Gee,
I'd like to be a businessman." Here you
meet a composer and you say, "Man, if
there's one thing I want to be, it's a
composer." So you're a businessman and a
sculptor and a bull fighter and a
composer and all those things. But
that's not you. You never give anyone a
chance to really like you or not like
you because you never even let them in
to see the first wall. You never say,
"Hey, step right this way and see the
real Jimmy Dean."
So, what's hiding in the middle, Jimmy?
Why do you shut people out?
Why don't you think you deserve
anything?
You think you're so dull that if they
get inside, they won't find anything and
they'll walk out on you? Is that why you
run out on them before they get too
close?
Do you think you're empty, Jimmy?
Is that why you're so scared?
So Jimmy told his writer friend that the
one thing he really wanted to be was a
writer and he flew to Indiana
in Fairmont. He put on his farm clothes
and listened to the stories people told.
Stories about himself as a boy.
And the old feelings came back.
the empty feeling of being the outcast.
He went back to his old high school. To
deserve his success, he had to believe
in his talent.
But nothing the critics wrote could make
him feel he had the right to be called
the genius boy that everyone said he
was.
Maybe if he could discover some talent
in his family, he might believe.
He made this tape recording secretly.
The microphone was hidden in his sleeve.
So listen closely.
>> You know, I played a I played a grandma
and I played a character uh in the movie
East. His name was Cal.
>> Yeah.
>> And just before I come out here, the
whole story. What I wanted to ask you,
you know, I went by the cemetery and
there's a there's a name out there, you
know, my great granddaddy
>> grandpa
>> and uh named Cal Dean.
>> Yeah.
>> And it so funny, you know, I played the
character Cal and Cal was your father.
>> What was he like? Did he have any u
Did he have any interest in art or
anything?
>> No.
>> You know, arty kind of kid or what? What
kind of guy was he? His auctioneer is
one of the best.
>> He was one of the best auctioneers ever
I've heard and I've had hundreds of
them.
>> Well, what's it take to be a good
auctioneer?
>> What's it take to be a good auctioneer?
>> You got to be a good judge of stock. You
got to be a judge of human nature.
You've got to have a talent of it.
>> Well, do a little bit of it. How you
doing?
>> Suppose you start with $5 on that. You
say five, five and a quarter. We'll give
you five, five and a quart. How they go
and two two and a half two and a half
two and a half two and a half
$6.
>> I'll tell you what kills auctioneers.
You take a man that talks to the public
every day
and he'll eventually get too much
confidence in himself.
You pull a lot of stuff and think he's
getting by with it, but he ain't. And as
soon as the people find out that you are
doing it, he'll quit you. That's what
kills all of them. That's what kills an
actor, too. Same thing. You got to be an
honest man along with
But it didn't fill his emptiness.
When he looked at Mary, he saw his own
childhood gazing back at him.
And he could give the boy the same
affection he wanted others to give him.
What's hiding in the middle, Jimmy? Why
do you have to shut people out? Why
don't you think you deserve anything?
>> Because I'm bad.
She wouldn't have died on me if I hadn't
been bad. She would have loved me and
taken care of me.
If she couldn't love me, nobody can.
I've been bad all my life, so I've never
deserved anything good.
But these feelings belonged in his
childhood.
As a man, he knew that he had never been
bad.
His mother had loved him. She died
because she had to, and it hadn't been
his fault.
Once he had dared to look at the past,
he was able to lay it away with his
nightmares in the attic trunk where it
belonged.
He looked at the statue he had made and
he saw that the face he was searching
for had always been right there.
a good face,
a nice face.
He knew he need no longer be ashamed
because there was more than emptiness
inside.
Now it was almost possible to believe
what people said of him. And he showed
everybody in giants. Showed them that
for all is evil, a man can still contain
beauty.
showed them the things he had learned as
a boy.
How to pace off a field as his uncle
Marcus had taught him.
He could accept his stardom now.
It was his right to have it.
When he came back to Hollywood, he used
his new position to make a traffic
safety film for television.
>> How fast will your car go?
>> Oh,
in honest miles an hour clocked run
about 1067.
>> You've won a few races, haven't you?
>> Oh, one or two.
>> Where?
>> Well, I showed pretty good at Palm
Springs. I ran a Bakersfield. People say
racing is dangerous, but I'll take my
chances on the track any day than on a
highway.
>> Well, Gig, I think I better take off.
>> Oh, wait a minute, Jimmy. Um, one more
question. Do you have any special advice
for the young people who drive?
>> Take it easy driving. The life you might
save might be mine.
and he bought a new car,
>> Jimmy. And I believe it was his mechanic
or
his other driver
were uh sitting here in the last booth
over there and he was telling me about
he's going up to um I don't recall the
name of the town. I think it was in
Bakersfield or somewhere up in that way
for this race. And Carmen, our chef,
said, "Well, Jimmy, we won't see you
tomorrow, so I'll make you something to
eat." And uh following day, I believe it
was right.
>> The road to Selenus follows the
bottomland.
He rose past the hills of the Diablo
Range.
Giant was finished and he was allowed to
drive again.
He was going to race his brand new car.
A policeman stopped him once for
speeding.
And he had paused to stretch in the sun
and drink a cup of coffee at a truckline
cafe.
He felt good.
He knew someone would feed his cat while
he was gone.
He knew his horse was out in comfortable
pasture.
But he couldn't remember if he had made
his bed or left the breakfast dishes in
the sink.
traffic officer Ronald Nelson of the
California Highway Patrol. He reads his
actual report written at the scene of
the accident. I received the call at
5:59 p.m.
It occurred on US 466 at the
intersection of 41, Friday, September
the 30th, 1955.
It was a sideswipe head-on collision.
>> These are official police photos.
>> There were two persons injured.
and one killed.
Number one injured was Donald Jean
Turnupseed, driver of vehicle number
one. Number two injured was Ralph
Witherick, a passenger in the Dean car.
The dead was James Byron Dean, DOA or
dead on arrival at the hospital.
He returned to his source and his
beginnings.
A quiet land to come home to,
a place to replenish himself.
Margie said
>> he came back here about five times, if
you want to count this one.
>> The town was silent.
The minister said
>> his brief career was as bright as a
meteor which flows like a golden tear
down the dark cheeks of night. His
porebears were his basketball team.
Of all the harvests the farm had grown,
the most plentiful was the boy himself.
What is the summation of this life?
the less than 300 months of time it took
to spend itself.
The 24 Christmas trees it saw
the thousands of mornings it looked out
upon
the legacy of art it left and stamped
with its own signature.
What can we say of him?
We can say that he despised the things
he was
and loved the things he was trying to
become.
We can say that he left two cherished
gifts.
He was able to do what few in his
generation had done before.
to reach into a dark theater and let
each person know that they were not
alone.
And he was able to unveil that single
quality which most of us conceal.
The wonderful sense of our own
inexpressable sweetness.
He brings us these gifts for the last
time which he made for East of Eden. It
has never been shown before.
Jimmy is deep in the shadows at the
start of the scene. Listen,
you're the one that dad loves.
He doesn't love me. Never has.
This is my son.
Erin, that is thinks I got a great idea
here. This
mother son, Cal,
who saved his money when we were kids
and bought him a beautiful jack knife.
And you got him a
Oh, lousy
mangy little old dog you picked up
somewhere.
Well, he loved that dog. Aaron,
he didn't even say thank you for my jack
knife.
Say nothing.
What have you ever done to deserve dad's
love?
What I mean is
like who used to be decent to him and
and try to make things halfway pleasant?
>> You're dead.
>> And And what have you done?
Ever since I I can remember you you you
growled at him and and snapped at him.
You can't win anybody's love by by
fighting them every minute.
You got to fight with them. You got to
show them that you're on their side.
Cal,
why don't you give dad a chance? Why
don't you show him that you love him?
>> How?
It's so easy.
Just tell him.
Show him.
Why don't you do something for it?
It's so easy.
>> You'll see. It's the simplest thing in
the world.
>> I know it.
I know it is. Aaron,
>> J's own words are his best epitap.
>> I'm trying to find the courage to be
tender in my life.
I know that violent people are weak
people.
Only the gentle are ever really strong.